Dr Rachael W Cheung, MBChB, MSc, MSc

Department of Psychology, Lancaster University, UK General Medical Council: registered clinician, non-practising r.w.cheung@lancaster.ac.uk https://cheungrw.github.io

Summary: I am a multi-disciplinary early career researcher with a sincere passion for conducting research about early experiences. My research investigates the environment surrounding language acquisition and how it affects the cognitive processes and behaviour of caregivers and their children. I also conduct research regarding more general learning mechanisms, and have a particular interest in comparing typical and atypical development and outcomes across a wide range of fields, including language development and psychiatry.

Education

2017 - current Leverhulme Trust Doctoral Scholar (Psychology PhD student)

Lancaster University

Thesis (provisional title): Characterising language learning and language outcomes in typical and atypical development

Supervisors: Professor Padraic Monaghan, Dr Calum Hartley (Department of Psychology, Lancaster University)

2014 - 2016 Developmental Neuroscience & Psychopathology MSc (Distinction)

University College London

Thesis: The effect of videogames on attention and resting state functional connectivity in adolescent males

Principle Investigator: Dr Michelle Hampson (Yale Magnetic Resonance Research Centre, Yale School of Medicine, Yale University)

2006 - 2012 Medicine MBChB

University of Manchester

2010 - 2011 Healthcare Ethics & Law MSc (Distinction)

University of Manchester (medical intercalation)

Thesis: Medical expert witnesses & clinical negligence: a time for change? Supervisor: Dr Catherine Stanton (School of Law, University of Manchester)

Prizes & Awards

2019 Faculty of Science and Technology Dean's Award for PhD Excellence

For outstanding performance in PhD

2017 - current Leverhulme Trust Doctoral Scholarship

Value per annum: maintenance stipend (£14,553), tuition fees (£4,195) and

research budget (approx. £5,000)

2011 Lord David Alliance Prize

For outstanding performance and best mark in Healthcare Ethics & Law MSc

Employment

Feb 2017 - Feb 2018 Emergency Medicine – Locum Doctor (A&E Agency; SHO)

Salford Royal NHS Foundation Trust; Stockport NHS Foundation Trust

Jan - June 2017 Associate Medical Writer

Ashfield Healthcare Communications

Aug - Dec 2016 Core Trainee Psychiatry Doctor (CT1) - portfolio available

Pennine Care NHS Trust

Aug 2012 - Aug 2014 Foundation Doctor (FY1, FY2) - portfolio available

Tameside & Glossop Acute Services NHS Foundation Trust

General Medicine & Endocrinology, General & Colorectal Surgery, Trauma & Orthopaedics, Paediatrics, General Practice (Community), Emergency

Medicine

Research Projects

2017 – current Leverhulme Trust Doctoral Scholar

Babylab / Department of Psychology, Lancaster University, UK

Longitudinal project: Predicting language outcomes in late talkers and

characterising how they learn (infant and child studies)

Cross-sectional projects: Gestures and multiple cues in word learning

(infant and adult studies)

With: Professor Padraic Monaghan, Dr Calum Hartley

<u>Methods</u>: Eye-tracking, behavioural, video-coding mother-infant interactions, standardised testing, touch-screen behaviours

2015 – 2016 Clinical Research Fellow

Yale Child Study Centre / Yale Magnetic Resonance Research Centre,

Yale University, USA

Longitudinal project: The effect of electronic media on attention and fMRI in

children and adolescents

<u>With</u>: Dr Linda Mayes, Dr Todd Constable, Dr Dennis Sukhodolsky, Dr Mike Crowley, Dr Dustin Scheinost, Chris Walsh, and Dr Michelle Hampson

Methods: Functional MRI (resting state functional connectivity), behavioural

Research Skills

Programming: R (proficient)

Analysis: General linear and mixed effect models, linear mixed effect models

Growth curve analysis of longitudinal data

Eye-tracking data analysis (HDF-conversion, fixation data; AOI based; growth

curve analysis)

Software: Analysis – SPSS

Eyetracking – Tobii Studio (Tobi X3-120) Task programming – E-Prime, PsychoPy3 Neuroimaging analysis – Biolmage Suite Research – Qualtrics, NIH Toolbox

Video-coding - ELAN

Other: Microsoft Office, Adobe Photoshop

Publications

- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (under review) Caregivers use gesture contingently to support infant word learning
- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (2020) The early cue catches the word: how gesture supports cross-situational word learning. *Proceedings of the 42nd Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society.*
- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (2019) Environmental effects on parental gesture and infant word learning. In A.K. Goel, C.M. Seifert, & C. Freksa (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 41st Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society*, 212-218.
- Humphreys, J., Obeney-Williams, J., **Cheung, R.W.**, Shah, N. (2016) Perinatal psychiatry: a new specialty or everyone's business? *BJPsych Advances* 22(6), 363-372.

Oral Presentations

- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (2019) Environmental effects on parental gesture and infant word learning. *Talk presented at CogSci 2019, Montreal, Canada.*
- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (2019) Environmental effects on parental gesture and infant word learning. *Talk presented at LCICD 2019 (Lancaster Conference on Infant and Early Child Development), Lancaster, UK.*
- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (2019) Word learning in typical and atypical development. *Talk presented at Department of Linguistics, University of Amsterdam, the Netherlands.*
- **Cheung, R.W**. (2017) A Junior Doctor's Perspective on Neuroscience and Psychiatry. *Talk presented with Professor Wendy Burn and Dr Gareth Cuttle, Royal College of Psychiatrists (Gatsby/Wellcome Neuroscience Implementation Project) at Lancashire Care NHS Trust, UK.*
- **Cheung, R.**, Constable, T., Mayes, L., Scheinost, D., Crowley, M., Hampson, M. (2016). From Mortal Kombat to Minecraft: Video games, Attention, and Resting State Functional Connectivity in Adolescent Males. *Talk presented at Yale School of Medicine, Yale University, USA*.

Posters

Cheung, R.W., Hartley, C., Dunn, K., Frost, R.L.A., Monaghan, P. (2019) Environmental effects on parent teaching and infant word learning. *Poster presented at WILD 2019 (Workshop on Infant*

Language Development), Potsdam, Germany.

- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Dunn, K., Frost, R.L.A., Monaghan, P. (2019) Preliminary results: environmental effects on parent teaching and infant word learning. *Poster presented at LCICD 2018 (Lancaster Conference on Infant and Early Child Development), Lancaster, UK.*
- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (2018) Environmental effects on parent teaching and infant word learning. Poster presented at the FST Postgraduate Conference, Lancaster, UK.
- **Cheung, R.**, Constable, T., Mayes, L., Scheinost, D., Crowley, M., Hampson, M. (2016). From Mortal Kombat to Minecraft: Video games, Attention, and Resting State Functional Connectivity in Adolescent Males. *Poster presented at Yale School of Medicine, Yale University, USA.*
- **Cheung W.**, Pramanik K., Warner R., Barton S., Trehan A. (2010) Converting Criticism to Change: Health Services Research in an Emergency Assessment Unit. Poster presented at 4th International Society of Acute Medicine Conference, Edinburgh, UK.

Public Engagement & Research Dissemination

2017 – 2020	Babylab Lancaster Coffee Mornings (monthly free event for families) Volunteer
2020	REF 2021 ICS (Faculty of Health and Medicine, Lancaster University) Scientific Writer
	I work directly with authors to identify and communicate key research impacts for the Research Excellence Framework Impact Case Studies
2019	LCICD 2019 (Lancaster Conference: Infant & Early Child Development) Organising committee member
2019	ESRC Festival of Science Volunteer demonstrator for Babylab Lancaster
2019	Campus in the City 2019 Volunteer demonstrator
2018	The Communication Trust: Using Evidence on the Ground Consultant with LuCiD and Professor Monaghan

I worked with speech and language therapists across the country, helping them select and evaluate interventions for early language skills (ages 0-5). I worked closely with a speech and language team that was piloting interventions for language delay in an Opportunity Area in Derby

2016 - 2018 Royal College of Psychiatrists: Gatsby/Wellcome Trust Neuroscience
Project Implementation Group
RCPSYCH Appointed Member

I served as a committee member for an implementation group designed to integrate up-to-date neuroscientific research into psychiatry training

Teaching (portfolio available)

Summary: I am a self-driven, highly motivated, and enthusiastic teacher who has extensive experience in teaching both on-the-job and formally in tutorials, lectures, and seminars. I have always designed my own teaching materials (slides, hand-outs, group exercises) based upon curricula, and have used my initiative to ensure these sessions are engaging as well as informative. My additional roles as a representative have afforded me a good sense of pastoral care, and I have consistently positive student feedback for my teaching (available on request).

Awarded 2019	Associate Fellow of the Higher Education Academy (ref. PR169537) Associate Teacher Programme, Lancaster University
2020 - current	Lancaster Medical School, Lancaster University, UK 2 nd Year Problem-Based Learning tutor (weekly)
2018 - 2020	Lancaster Medical School, Lancaster University, UK 3 rd Year Psychiatry tutorial leader (Mental Health Law, Personality Disorders, Case and Poster presentations)
2017 - 2020	Department of Psychology, Lancaster University, UK 2 nd Year 205 Developmental Psychology Seminars, Associate Lecturer 1 st Year 101 Developmental Psychology Seminars, Associate Lecturer 1 st Year 101 Skills in Psychology, Associate Lecturer
2020	Department of Linguistics, Lancaster University, UK 2 nd Year 228 Language Acquisition: Language Impairments, Guest Lecturer
2013 - 2018	Salford Royal NHS Foundation Trust, UK Tameside and Glossop Acute Services NHS Foundation Trust, UK $3^{\rm rd}-5^{\rm th}$ year medical students, University of Manchester I delivered informal teaching throughout my clinical years to medical students on placement, and have had numerous students shadow me alongside doing my day-to-day job
2012 - 2014	Tameside and Glossop Acute Services NHS Foundation Trust, UK Junior doctor (FY1) tutorials: coroner's court, acute on-call conditions 5 th Year (final) medical student tutorials, University of Manchester: OSCE stations, history taking, clinical examinations, acute presentations/management of disease, interpreting ABGs/test results
2009 - 2011	Medi-Quest Ethics & Law Tutor, Salford Royal NHS Foundation Trust UK Group-based tutorials for secondary school students (14 – 18-years-old)
Representative Roles	
2019 - 2020	Postgraduate Research Student Representative (Lancaster University)
2016	Junior Doctor Representative & Local Negotiating Committee Representative (Pennine Care NHS Trust)
2012 - 2014	Foundation Trainee Representative (Tameside and Glossop Acute Services NHS Foundation Trust)

Volunteer Work & Other Interests

2010 - 2011 Mediscope (Manchester Medical School Magazine) Editorial & Writing Team

2008 - 2012 Barnabus Manchester (homeless and red light district outreach) – weekly volunteer

Languages: English (native); Cantonese (dim sum level); German (A1 level)

Music: Piano (grade 7), cello (grade 5), guitar (self taught)